all right hello and welcome
everyone it is October 24th 2023 and
we're an act in live stream number 55.0
on realizing synthetic active inference
agents okay welcome to the active
inference Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at some of the links on this page this
is a recorded in an archive live stream
so please provide feedback so we can
improve our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome and we'll be
following video etiquette for live
streams head over to active inference
dorg if you want to learn more about
participating in live streams or other
activities all right well we're in live
stream 55
series with a goal to learn and discuss
these two very interesting papers on
realizing synthetic active inference
agents part one on epistemic objectives
and graphical specification part two on
the variational message updates as with
all videos it's an introduction for some
of the ideas not a review or a final
word we're gonna introduce oursel then
jump into a fairly lengthy background
section that will prepare us to ask the
questions and get to a place where the
figures cont or the papers contributions
can be figured out so let us begin with
introducing ourself and saying hi and
saying maybe something that was exciting
to us or made us want to participate in
this series so I'm Daniel I'm a
researcher in California and I was
interested to go a little deeper on
message passing it's something that's
brought up a lot in the textbook and
implicitly in other papers but this was
an opportunity to tackle it head on and
I'll pass to
Bert yeah so I'm ber uh I study civil
engineering in the
Netherlands um and I struggle with the
math of active inference but recently I
picked up reinforcement learning and
together with this paper I think it
really
helps and Y
hi I'm yakob I'm also a researcher in
California and I'm really excited about
this paper from a number of different
angles I guess the graphical notation
and the notation the paper introduces I
think can have um really profound impact
on the field from both a computational
and a um theoretical Viewpoint and um
interested to um learn more about the
implications of um the new notation for
for the
research yeah new notation just
dropped okay there's a pair of papers as
mentioned and the information is here so
each of us can phrase the big question
that brought us to the paper but I wrote
it this way which is right there in the
title there's at least a triple play a
triple
ponre and there's a diad of papers so
what is this realizing in the context of
the title well in one sense we're
realizing
something in terms of implementing it or
manifesting it they're deploying
something that is being realized so
there's a accomplishment sense of
realizing also the work calls attention
to our own realizing process our
relevance realization how we come to
appreciate and interact with synthetic
intelligence
ours and then we're also talking about
building agents that do some kind of
realizing in themselves like realizing
agents in that sense so what kind of
inning starts off with a triple
play I don't
know Bert or yakup what
big questions brought you to the paper
what do you think the paper takes
on um I think in terms
of creating scalable active inference
models that are
reproducible um across a variety of
settings is quite um exciting so maybe
realizing in that sense across a number
of different domains uh is part of um
part of the meaning here um and of
course the triple play uh that we were
exploring with our own work from going
from just a simple graphical
representation to a mathematical
description of the generative model and
the algorithm for message passing and
updating the generative model through
time uh to then a code implementation
that can be deployed in various Dynamic
setting
um
that um is also um what I think is in
important part of uh of this
paper oh yeah and uh for me especially
as not an expert on active inference but
someone is more interested in applying
it uh their work on working towards a p
torch of active inference is really
valuable and I think uh their way of
deconstructing the mechanisms of uh
expected and variational energy and to
combine them into one function makes it
uh simplifies it a lot I
think cool so we're going to look deeper
at the papers of course soon but
just a few of the aims of the
paper part one they construct a purely
synthetic approach to the otive
inference framework motivated from the
point of view of engineering rather than
neurobiology and we're going to talk
about what synthetic is and in part two
they use a variety of
technical phenomena variational calculus
message
passing and reactive programming to
simulate a perception action cycle on
the
Tas
okay one of you would you like to read
the first abstract and then the other
can read the other abstract whoever
wants to go
first um I can read the the first one so
the free energy principle Fe is a
theoretical framework for describing how
intelligent systems self-organize into
coherent stable structures by minimizing
a free energy functional active
inference is a coroller of the F that
specifically details how systems that
are able to plan for the future agents
function by minimizing particular free
energy functionals that incorporate
information seeking components this
paper is the first in a series of two
where we derive a synthetic version of
active inference on free form factor
graphs the present paper focuses on
deriving a local version of the free
energy functionals used for active
inference this enables us to construct a
version of active inference which
applies to arbitrary graphical models
and interfaces with prior work on
message passing algorithms the resulting
messages are derived in our companion
paper we also identify a gap in the
graphical notation used for Factor
graphs while Factor graphs are great at
expressing a generative model they've so
far been unable to specify the full
optimization problem including
constraints to solve this problem we
developed constraint forny style Factor
graph cffg notation which permits a
fully graphical description of
variational inference objectives we then
proceed to show how uh cfgs can be used
to reconstruct prior algorithms for
active inference as well as derive new
ones the latter is demonstrated by
deriving an algorithm that permits
direct policy inference for active
inference agents circumventing A
long-standing scaling issue that has so
far hindered the application of active
inference in an industrial setting we
demonstrate our algor gorithm on the
classic t-m task ensure that it
reproduces the information seeking
behavior that is a Hallmark feature of
active
inference thank you and the second
paper H yes so the free energy principle
describes biological agents as
minimizing variation of free energy with
respect to a generative model of the
environment active inference is a Cora
of the FP that describes how agents
explore and exploit the envir M by
minimizing an expected free energy
objective in two related papers we
describe a scalable epistemic approach
to synthetic active inference agents by
message passing on free from for style
Factor graphs fgs a companion paper part
one introduces a constrainted FFG
otation that visually represents free
energy objectives for active inference
the current paper derives message
passing algorithms that minimize
generalized free energy objectives on a
constraint uh for an effector graph by
variational
calculus a comparison between simulated
bet and uh generaliz free energy agents
illustrates
synthe behavior on a team ma navigation
task with full message passing accounts
of synthetic active inference agents it
becomes possible to derive and reuse
message updates across models and move
closer to Industrial applications of
synthetic active
inflence great thank you here's the road
map section titles of the first
paper here are the section headers of
the second
paper so before we jump into the
background and then the
papers let's just have one last train
stop what is
synthetic and what's synthetic about
active inference so as it being 2023 we
went to the language model and we asked
for some adjectives that are in the
semantic neighborhood of synthetic and
you can see them here artificial lab
created synthetic counterfeit phony
deceptive inauthentic
unnatural a lot of these are somewhat
negative associations semantically so
how does synthetic come to be
meaning something negative or
deceitful and then in what ways is that
a similar or a different sense of
synthetic then referring to the unified
compositionality of something that's
Blended and similarly we could talk
about artificial like artificial
intelligence is that artifice like
crafted or is it artificial like phony
bogus false so in the context of the
paper there's probably a bunch of
different ways that we can draw it with
the authors and a little bit here too
what is being synthesized if you have
any thoughts on this but what else might
be
synthetic it might refer to something
that's not just a hypothetical like a
real synthesis or realized synthesis it
might refer to information risk and
synthetic
intelligence it might refer to synthetic
judgments those whose predicates are
wholly distinct from their subjects
and then recently at The topos Institute
there was a great talk by Jonathan
Sterling synthetic domains in the 21st
century so there's a lot of very
interesting senses and ways that
synthetic is
used those preliminary thoughts
on about these
Pap these
papers um
I
think I guess building on uh what you
already said part of the synthesis uh
could be the
um decreasing the gap between the
mathematical description of a model and
its graphical representation and its
subsequent code implementation so the
focus on graphical models on constraint
forny sty Factor graph
um
combines the aspect of generalized re
energy or Bey free energy which uh is
motivated by a forny style graph
structure um with the actual
implementation of a synthetic agent uh
or an artificial agent in uh in code or
in synthetic settings which themselves
are trying to model some part of uh
reality who we'll
explore okay so to ber for background
part one and thank you for all the work
leading up to this. zero Bert so take it
away with the background just let me
know when to switch
slides yeah all right uh so for the
background of part one uh will Del into
what are base crafts then how do you do
inference over these
crafts and then the authors use uh make
extensive use of ouren to optimize uh
over the graph the for Vector
graph and then some miscellaneous stuff
uh that will be relevant too that play
smaller parts in the paper all right
next
slide so first off base cast uh working
up eventually to for graphs uh but
starting with the simplest one which is
just a b ban Network and then the
classical example is the yeah the
earthquake all yeah earthquake
network uh so you
can so each circle is a random variable
and they represent a particular state so
whether for example the alarm goes off
yes or
no uh and these variables can be
continuous or discrete
and so the total generative model is the
joint probability of all these random
variables and you can factorize them so
they only relate to uh one or two or
several others at least a limited set of
other
variables and I'm moving on from that is
the hidden Mark of model where you add
uh time so you have multiple time steps
so in this case X1 x0 X1 X2 and and this
works on the The Mark of assumption
which is that all the relevant
information of the past is in the
current time step so you only need to to
consider the
current and on top of that you can only
uh you cannot observe it in stats
directly so you need uh yeah observation
Arrow so that's the
E and then the next step building on top
of the hit Mark of model is that
partially observable Mark of decision
process which is a lot of
words um but really it's the same where
you have a hidden State s with an
observable State and you transition from
States but now you add an action and the
action acts the
policy and it acts on uh the B the
transition so for an example would be I
expect S1 to have a certain value given
my action and this observation O2 should
be in line with
that and the policy selected using the
expected free
energy all right next
slide and then how do you actually
figure out uh the values of a base graph
and that requires
inference and there are multiple ways so
the first one is exact inference which
is what you would do if you uh calculate
by pen and paper which is really only
practical for small discrete models like
the the example model on the last slide
and if if you want to go to bigger
models more complex models you need
approximate
inference and within that Monte Carlo
sampling is a a key pillar and there a
bunch of algorithms that applied that
use
it but the core idea is the same you
sample many times from an idealist
distribution to approximate another
distribution of
Interest another method is method which
uh you may be familiar with this
variation of free energy which yeah
active inference us a lot and then you
indirectly minimize the difference
between two distributions using the K
Divergent oh yeah you try to minimize
the kale Divergence but you cannot do
that directly so instead uh yeah you
maximize the
elbow and this works with a family of
distributions and a family is for
example a cians or exponentials which
you have to pick
one and I'm better free energy
uh works on this it's also a free energy
but it has the assumption that only
local interactions matter so instead of
going over entire generative model you
only look at one factorized part at a
time and optimization which is also used
in the paper uh to find some parameters
and is Newton's method but you have a
function and you want to know where this
function goes through the x-axis so you
can take the slope
and
iteratively uh take more slopes until
you get at approximately the point where
it goes to the
x-axis all right next
slide and then authors
use paper so to quickly introduce this
it is a method to describe an objective
function with
constraints uh so and the first
derivative of the Lin
if you set it equal to zero those are
the optimal
points so that would be where the blue
and red curve intersect in this
picture and the Loni multiplier Lambda
is the rate of change to objective
objective function would change if you
relax the
constraint so in this example it will be
the same as changing the constant B of
the the head
function um so
concretely if the Lambda was positive
here then increasing B would result in
objective function also increasing so
you have some leeway to work to improve
the function even further so you can
optimize more that's what it's
saying righty next
slide and that's some miscellaneous
stuff um so the term entropy is used a
lot especially in terms of epistemic
foraging but for now it's just a measure
of how uncertain a distribution
is and in general sampling and uncertain
distribution gives you more information
and sampling a certain one for example
if it rains every day seeing rain again
doesn't tell you much because it rains
every day
anyway a direct Delta function is a
probability distribution that is one for
a single point and zero
elsewhere and then a statistical moment
um
I justly in mathematics the moments of a
function are certain quantitative me
measures related to the shape of a
function's graph if a function is a
probability distribution then the first
moment is the expected value so the
average the second is the central moment
of variance the standard deviation the
third is the skus and the four is the
curosis and then finally the coolback
light control which is a ter from
control theory
which basically attempts uh to make a
system converge to a set
prior and adusted by minimizing the K
Divergence
yes thank you great background so that
kind of speed
runs basian stats first layer now we're
going to head into a second layer of
background that's going to bring us into
the the for KN graph space and after the
second background part we'll be in a
position to understand two papers a
little better so here's the big picture
on background part
two even with all of background part one
in hand there's also some more modern
important ACM as well as non-ac INF
related advances that are going to get
us up to speed so for a lot of the
concepts here we're just over it first
and then we'll be talking more to the
authors about them and so I'll take a
more narrative overview of recent
updates and then we'll steer towards the
technical so first graphical models
active inference and belief propagation
over the last years Carl friston at all
have been collaborating with the lab and
collaborators of bird the right and
around 2017 they released several very
important papers one was a factor graph
description of deep temporal active
inference and another was the graphical
brain belief propagation and active
inference so as ber alluded to earlier
many of the operations or formalisms of
active inference can be understood as
manipulations of parameters or variables
that might reflect data like
observations priors precisions different
kinds of variables and that is given
exact form in the graphical model
specifically the basian graph and here
we see the familiar figure 4.3 from the
2 uh 2022 textbook um now the nodes on
that graphical model are variables and
edges are their causal or their
informational relationship and so
especially after Pearl at all and the
causal modeling developments in the
1980s and
90s this was adapted into a
probabilistic or cybernetic setting
where certain nodes on this graph were
associated with action with perception
with cognitive phenomena and so this is
a causal Model A basian graphical model
it's the kind of thing that we see in
very many active inference
papers now the basian graph is awesome
it allows us to tackle some really
challenging compute problems get a lot
of semantic interpretability and so on
however there's also a few limitations
or challenges in execution so first just
emically there's some side information
that is needed to provide in order to
get to a fully reproducible basian cical
simulation and live stream
54 shows how that information is
provided formally by category Theory but
more to the pragmatic point for this
discussion in actual computational
execution whether you're running that
Bas graph on a single core single thread
or whether you're using multiple
computing
elements a given or a particular
generative model must be implemented in
a certain way or order if we were doing
a single agent or a multi-agent
simulation we might wonder so should we
update the perception of everybody and
then let everybody make action or should
we do action and perception of number
one then number two then number three
but then isn't that unfair because then
isn't one of them always getting to see
an act first and so on so just drawing
the graph doesn't give you the actual
order of operations to carry it out
reproducibly so that under specification
of the basian graphical Logistics or
scheduling leads to a lot of degrees in
Freedom in model deployment now this
might be an issue or not be an issue for
any given task however whether you use
an off-the-shelf or a custom solution to
address this challenge these different
approaches might take time they might
not transfer they might not be General
and so on also there might be different
simulation outcomes or different
computational costs that happen when you
implement the same graphical model
differently so that Li limits High
reliability use and also transfer and
then lastly kind of related the
computational complexity estimations are
difficult to understand just by looking
at the base graph it'd be really nice if
there was a way to have the model and
then know how much it's going to cost or
take to
run so enter the forny factor
graphs in 2001 for wrote a technical
paper called codes on graphs normal
realizations just like normal 2001 stuff
and this introduced some fundamental
components let's ask the authors and
find out what exactly those fundamental
moves were but what was introduced LED
to the development of what is now called
a forny factor graph FFG or a normal
graph again another interesting question
how is normal being used
here the forny factor graph
representation is dual or
informationally equivalent to Any Given
basian graph importantly though ffg's
enable message passing message passing
provides node local and whole graph
scheduling logistics for messages in a
way that allows for more tractability in
execution importantly these messages are
being passed amongst variables at a very
granular level this is not referring to
like two bounded agents sending each
other a postcard
simply the network or the graph it's a
very general data structure so it's not
surprising that we're going to be
encountering multiple kinds of graphs
but it is relevant to know which kinds
of graphs we're talking about
and because this FFG representation can
be applied to anywhere a basian graph is
used people have applied both basing
graphs and to a lesser or more recent
extent for Factor graphs to a bunch of
different statistical problems like
filtering smoothing prediction mdp PDP
and so on so to kind of lock this in
here we see on the right figure 7.3 from
our Zulo in friston's textbook so this
is the standard discrete time partially
observable marov decision process and on
the left here is a figure from The
graphical brain paper of 2017 so across
the top these two basian graphs are
actually identical they're the same
exact type of graph and they're both the
same base graph and then the 2017 figure
shows that that base
graph has this one to one relationship
with a for Factor
graph what is the difference with a for
Factor graph wh why do we need to have a
different format to describe what might
at first glance appear to be the same
information let's go to graphical brain
2017 we use graphical representations to
characterize message passing under deep
generative models that might be used by
the brain we use three sorts of graphs
to emphasize the form of generative
models one the nature of Basi and belief
updating two and how this might be
accomplished in neuronal circuits three
so here's the three sorts of graphs that
they're going to talk
about first basian networks or
dependency graphs that's the one that we
see the most commonly nodes correspond
to unknown variables edges denote
dependencies amongst
variables 40 Factor graphs
have nodes that represent local
functions or factors of a probability
distribution over random variables while
edges come to represent variables per se
or more exactly a probability
distribution over those variables and
finally neural networks have nodes that
are constituted by the sufficient
statistics of unknown variables and
other auxilary variables like prediction
errors while the edges in those graphs
denote in exchange of the functions of
sufficient statistics
crucially these graphical
representations are formally equivalent
in the sense that any basian network can
be expressed as a factor graph and any
message passing on a factor graph can be
depicted as a neural
network however as we will see later the
various graphical formulations offer
different perspectives on belief
updating or
propagation so this is a very rich
topic this background section was to say
that forny Gra graphs have a
different style or format than basian
graphs however they exist in this dual
relationship so there's things like
algorithms and procedures that you can
do on FFG that you can't do on Bas
graphs but it's all good because you can
go from the Bas graph to the FFG
representation and then Implement some
procedure on the
FFG
so let's get to the
papers the background one and background
two sections have got us to perhaps the
point where we're very excited to see
how the authors implemented fly
synthetic active inference agents using
message passing logistical and
operational scheduling algorithms on
forny Factor graphs
representing basian graphical models
crafted to calculate a constrained Beth
free energy as a generalized or unified
free energy imperative unifying the
variational and the expected free energy
for sense making and decision- Mak in
active inference
agents so now we're heading into another
double movement of the coming to papers
the first paper is itself going to be
like a background and a notational paper
but also one that adds to the
literature and then the second paper
will make the addition on top of the
advance of the first paper so lot of
material let's go into the first
paper yes so uh for the first paper
we'll be going uh over at chapter by
chapter to start with setting up
thein then defining uh yeah the
epistemic objective and how to include
it in a a synthetic agent then in
chapter 4 they layout what it mean what
like Lan active inference means in
chapter 5 they
uh describ the the notation for the
constraint foror
graph and six they highlight why the
original
generalized by classical active
inference and the original generalized
three energy algorithm are special cases
of the loin active inference so of
definition of the for effector
graph and then in seven they do an
experiment uh for policy
inference yeah um and for chapter two
the the conent approach to message
passing uh so as Daniel described for
Factor graphs represent a factorized
function over variables which you can
see in equation one and figure one uh so
on the left you see equation one uh that
shows per note where V is uh so a is a
note in the set of all nodes
V and so on the right you can see the
image uh which says that each note is
aor of all the variables and the
variables are on edges and that's really
important and as mentioned in the
background approximate inference is used
in this case variational inference and
so we start with a free energy function
an equation
three on the left which is used to
approximate variational distribution qar
and qar is the optimal uh distribution
that we want to get to and we uh
achieved it by minimizing
it uh and so be free energy is distinct
from variation of free energy by
factorizing the calculation of free
energy so instead of computing it all by
once out once you comput it uh per note
and Edge and then at the results which
you can see on the
he each local free energy will include
entropy terms from all connected
edges and since edges can be connected
to two nodes the entropy of these
variables would be counted twice so one
Edge is a variable and if you connected
to two nodes you would be counting the
same variable twice and so to cancel
that out uh they add the one minus
degree of the
edge and at the bottom added that and
normally an edge has always degree of
two which might be sound weird because
how can an edge have a degree because
normally nodes have deges um but in
chapter five we will show that it's
possible to have dangling edges that are
just that are not connected uh that are
not factorized on one end so it is
possible to have edges with degree
one and last uh three constraints ensure
that the sum of probabilities for each
note and Edge equals one and it's
normalization and also that it is
possible to retrieve Edge and note
probabilities from The Joint
distribution so that the edge says
something about the nodes and the noes
say something about the
edges yes next one cool yeah just have
something to say yeah just just that um
we have the variables on the edges of
this graph and the fs are like functions
or operations or little factories where
variables can come in potentially
multiple variables can come in and some
activity
happens but we're putting the variable
that would be in the node of the base
graph and we're having it on an edge
connecting
functions so again the information is
identical or
congruent but the everything that we're
going to see now is flipped in into this
space where the edges are the variables
and that's what it's going to enable the
node local
computations and then in chapter three
uh defining epistemic
objectives um the the artist writes that
ages interact with the world they
inhabit and until a generative model of
the environment achieving future goals
can be cast as free energy
minimization and then uh they asked the
question what should this free energy
functional look like and
why and that sets up the the rest of the
paper
basically uh only optimizing bad free
energy or variation of free energy does
not lead to exploration but K
control uh which means that only prior
values are
satisfied a Hallmark of active inference
is alternative functionals specifically
made for inferring policies like
expected free
enery uh which includes uh information
collection
and so epistemics arise from optim
optimization of approximate Mutual
information Mutual
information uh uh on the bottom right is
a metric like the r squ if you make a
linear and that it tells you
um it tells you how much one variable
relates to another
one and to go back uh M Mutual
information between x and z an equation
10 on the
left to work on it the uncertainty
entropy of
X
Set uh yeah that's in the height
equation so it's how much you know about
the one given that you know the
other and so say x is an observation and
Z is an internal
State then an agent can choose
X to see
about are related to each
other and then how do you how to define
a functional that comines battery enics
so to
have add negative Mutual
information and minimizing the free
energy functional the elbow with in
negative Mutual information means
maximizing the mutual information so
you're trying to get as much information
uh about internal and observation
States yeah just one comment there BT
and then y feel free to add anything
that's a great comparison you made with
the r squar for linear aggression so in
a linear aggression R squ summarizes how
much the two um axes the X and the Y AIS
resemble each other R squ of one means
they're exactly collinear they're AR a
manifold R square of Z is there's no
linear relationship and R squ of
negative one would be a negative
association mut information is kind of
like that but two characteristics are
importantly different first off you
can't
have on the worst thing that two things
could be or the least that they could be
is just noise to each other so you can
take the negative of the mutual
information but you can't have negative
information on something and then
secondly it's not a linear relationship
you could have something that is um an
inverted U and the linear aggression
might find that that had a low R squar
because the best regression line might
go through the middle of the U but then
if you just think about that a little
bit more generally of course one of
those variables has information on the
other variable and so it's kind of like
moving a lot of our intuition and also
some of the epistemic status of linear
regressions
into more of a pure information
geometric space and it's a really
important Point too that the vfe
doesn't endogenously have an epistemic
drive it's just about the realtime
surprise level of beliefs and incoming
data and so a Hallmark of active
inference is the construction of these
functionals such as expected free energy
or free energy of the expected future or
generalized free
energy
okay and so I expected free energy only
works for future time steps whereas uh
variational and bad free energy work for
past and the current time step and
instead the authors uh posted
generalized free energy uh works for
both the same time and it includes a
part that
tracks in equation 14 so that's on the
end you have P with a curvy stripe XK
and it basically keeps count of which
time step we are at at this current
moment and also note that um the policy
uh or
control uh is fixed so that's you with a
a hoof on
it and so past time steps have OB data
and are locked using the direct Delta
function which was the function with a
probability of one at a specific value
and zero at the rest whereas future time
steps are still open to be optimized
using generalized free
energy uh and so below that you can
see
this free energy how you lock uh some
values and keep them open at other
moments and so for a sneak peek uh on
the right and the figure in the right um
from paper two you can see that as time
goes on and time steps are observed data
constraints are added and that's the the
little black circle with the delta in
it and committing to a full model
specification are limits what a
generalized fre energy function can do
instead making it fully not local is
synthetic active inference as the AR
side
okay and then in chapter four they
discuss the Lin uh active
inference which is the key of the paper
uh and so with no node local generalized
free energy we can construct a Lin for
active inference and the goal is to have
a distributed inference proed procedure
solving for each node individually and
constraining this solution as show shown
in equation 13 so on the
right and we need to assume that actual
and approximate probabilities are about
equal to each other uh we had to make
that assumption so I guess we can ask it
next week and now uh with this messages
can be derived as done in part two which
is the next paper however in this paper
they attempt another way to arrive at
the no Lo node local generaliz free
energy and this is done in two steps so
first they apply a mean field
factorization uh that ensures edges are
independent for each node which you can
see on the right where you have the
factor of the node
Sr has a a product so for all edges so
they are independ and then the second
move they make is that you can partition
the connecting variables edges into two
sets one that is adjusted and the other
that is left alone and to the adjusted
set they apply P substitution which is
very
important and this basically replaces a
local free energy with a local
generalized free
energy and on the bottom uh is the
formula for applying P
substitution which I also don't fully
understand so maybe you guys know a
little more about
that definitely will ask
I'll just note here that the slash is
used to mean except for I hope this is
correct so here we're able to take
something that contains
all and we're able to kind of pull out
one with this more intractable
integral and then still do the simpler
log
but we'll
ask uh the second paper will show how P
substituted nodes are gradually removed
from the the F Factor graph over time as
these notes are now in the past and do
not need to consider consider the future
anymore again for sneak peek see on the
right uh everywhere you add the the
delta in the black circle you remove the
square and the square is the uh notation
for p
substitution and then to construct the
active inference Lin it is important
that P substituted nodes work with
different messages generalized free
energy instead of pet free energy and in
this way add
epistemics the optimal points of the Lin
where the first derivative is zero are
the stationary point of the message
passing
process which means that nodes do not
change anymore if you keep update
and so there a very long formula for the
Lin um and I said you split the nodes
into two one set that you be substitute
and the other that you
don't and on top of that you add three
constraints uh which have a LTA in in
front of them and that is the
marginalization the normalization of
both notes and I
just that's very important about the
station Ary point of message passing
being kind of like settled where
everybody can pass all the messages they
want and nothing is
changing and that's going to
be um probably leveraged in the reactive
message passing programming environment
where rather than needing to send all
messages once to the calculate and send
all messages again it opens up up the
ability for different regions of the
graph to be sending and receiving
messages at different frequencies so if
One sensor was sampling a thousand times
a second one was sampling one time per
second no longer do you have to decide
should we coar grain to 1 second or
should we waste 999 Cycles on the slower
cycle sensor now with reactive message
passing because there's no local
descriptions it's possible
to open up that implementational
space and now we'll get into defining
the notation for the constrainted for
Factor graphs and so foror graphs are
use useful for describing generative
models but it is important to know the
exact functional to be minimized and the
authors develop a new notation for
writing constraints directly as part of
the for Factor graph
because normal for Factor graphs do not
show that it's
just a figure four on the right builds
upon representing factors with squares
nodes and edges as variables that can be
factorized and they add circular beads
which indicate constraints that Define
our family q and that has to do with the
variational distribution a bead on an
edge denotes um yeah of the H QSI while
a bead in the center of a node is uh
qsa and then they build uh they
introduce four constraints that are
needed uh as notation for the for Factor
cph so the first one is a factorization
constraint uh and it can either be a
naive mean field or a structured mean
field when naive mean field is a
stronger uh
constraint which means that every factor
is independent which is figure five it's
above it's in the middle on the right
and uh structured is less strong because
you can factorize multiple variables
together and I added some example uh
formulas many edges like needed
for uh if you want to have many edges
many variables into a
factor uh they introduce the notation
with dots in between and this is useful
when you have for example a Garian
mixture model which is a bunch of uh
yeah
components we'll we'll see if this is uh
accurate but let's imagine these four
variables are coming in and meeting in
the factory four prerequisite components
of the car assembly
process the fully
factorized way to represent that is
shown here that's the mean field
assumption that we can just treat those
components separately like if what we
were doing was just multiplying or I
mean adding the numbers together maybe
we could treat them separately but then
also there are these
intermediate structural
factorizations where you can take four
joint coming in and then you could
separate it into these two are separate
and these two are connected or two
pairs so it gives you the expressivity
to do the Continuum from fully joint to
fully factorized mean field and
everything between all the combinations
in
between in a per node
fashion rather than at the whole graph
level whereas that is often how it's
discussed elsewhere somebody constructs
a big generative model and says and then
we took a meanfield
approach to the graph so here we have
that kind of expressivity in a given
node unmute then
continue good call H so the second is a
pH constraint uh which enforces a
particular uh yeah function uh or
distribution really on a local marginal
of an edge or a Lo
uh figure eight shows what enforcing
aing constraint on an edge looks like
and figure nine shows uh two different
constraints on the the notes and the
authors explicitly note that a
constraint on an edge is independent of
on the notes and that it factorizes into
and vice versa so uh the messages pass
and then after everything is done you
it's like squeezing clay into a box it
just has to fit but it's only after the
fact
effect and then they note dangling edges
which do not terminate on a note on one
side but um so they wouldn't require a
beat but you need it to be able to do a
form constraint so they still write them
in um and you have that's why they add a
sort of dummy Factor note on one
end and then the third constraint is a
Delta constraint
uh the Delta constraints and data points
allow us to incorporate measurements
into a
model equation 30 and figure 10 show
this for data constraints these are
special since they denote observations
and block the flow of messages so these
are these points are now fixed nothing
goes through it because it is already
set and then another option is that when
you don't know which value to fix it to
so uh the S I
had then you can optimize the value and
then it is called a Delta constraint and
the op optimization of this is don't
using expectation
maximization what I saw in this section
was let's just say that we were drawing
height observations
from a
forest so one way to think about that is
the the gaussian distribution that we're
drawing from okay but now you get the
data point and you could think about
that data point as just an entry and a
value you could also think of it as a
dirck Delta
distribution parameterized exactly by
the value of the data point and so
thinking about data as being a dero
constraint uh
variable where here the variables are on
edges brings unification between
empirical
uh data coming in from the outside or
passed around
internally and broader distributional
perspectives and then the fourth
constraint is moment matching which
replat the hard marginalization
constraint used to include the entropy
of edges and so this lo orginization as
now only the moments need to
align uh and equation 8 contains both
note and Edge terms since the moment
matching constraint applies to both at
the same time uh and they apply the both
at the same time because of the the top
uh
formula and the middle one the middle
formula
shows
uh the sufficient statistics described
by T capital T and so basically what
this means is that you pick a
distribution and you only pick the
moments so the first one would be the
mean of the distribution tion and the
second will be the the standard
deviation and so only those need to fit
you don't care about the
rest and P substitution is the final
piece needed to represent active infen
on a constraint for Factor graph and
constructing the local generalized free
energy using mean field factorization
and P substitution was only done to
represent the L active inference on aint
for
and recall that P substitution involves
substituting part of the model P for Q
in expectation only and that is the the
formula on the the bottom and it's
represented with a square in the for
Factor
graph and equ shows the substitution on
figure 13 replacing uh the local
variation of free energy with a local
generalized free
energy oh
replacing Q on the data or on y with P
that conditions on x and
z this red piece is being called
attention to and we'll we'll unpack that
more with the
authors and on top of that uh lastly the
the authors compress the the constraints
forc to make it easy to read and only
deviations relative to the default
battery energy are shown and the bechain
is introduced as a series of bead beads
connected by edges and is summarized if
it contains no extra information and the
authors go in really into depth but I
will just keep it to this where they go
from the left image to the right so the
right is the cleaned up F Factor graph
and then you can easy more easily
compress it and make it smaller for very
large
diagrams
yeah allow us to kind of compress or
skip through the uninformative parts and
just call attention to the new
information that's being
intersected then in chapter six they
highlight how classical active inference
and original generalized free energy
algorithm are special cases of the
developed lonian active
inference so an integral part of message
passing algs is the choice of a schedule
which Daniel already explained and the
which is the order of messages uh up in
which they are passed iterative methods
are sensitive to the order and thein
active inference is an iterative method
and might be sensitive to the choice of
schedule so choosing the schedule
carefully allows us to recover classical
active inference planning algorithms as
a special
case and figure 20 on Blow shows the
constraints for Factor graph as a
composite
note of a composite note for the Lin AC
inference on discrete State
spaces uh equation the equations on the
right show the corresponding factors
where ha is defined as a function of the
transition Matrix required for the other
equations and figure 21 shows the
message updates
uh some cannot be solved in closed form
and instead require multic estimates
uh U ofx is the average free energy of
the composite not and corresponds
exactly to expected free energy of us
and standard active
inference where a composite notes the
the block with striped yeah strip block
around it m of set and M of a are solved
differently than the rest they require c
bar is solved using Newton methods as it
tends to fluctuate between multiple
extreme and Ma is estimated using a
sampling procedure and so uh below shows
the generative model of a discrete
pump and the
equations uh to below that show the
factors and note again the head on U so
that the AES are
fixed and calculating the generalized
free energy is still using a forward
sweep which you can see with the arrows
arrows on the bottom right going from
left to right and summing the free
energy terms over all the substituted
composite
notes and these should then be equal to
the result from the shown
equation cool these images are just so
interesting even without knowing what
they
are
and reconstructing original generalized
free energy method is then a matter of
including past observations for past
time steps adding data
constraints while for future time steps
adding P
substitution and naan field is applied
to all the notes the schedule the order
of messages is shown
below the update equations of the
generalized free energy using this model
are the same as of the expected free
energy
and then the authors work on our example
uh which is the the classic teamm
task uh yeah so the tools in this paper
are not limited to restating prior work
uh it offers more advantages one of
which is the ability to directly infert
a policy instead of uhing post
hog selection uh choose using actions
which have the best energy
terms instead you can do it immediately
so the optimal action is to take is
therefore to visit
uh but the optimal action in the teamas
is to first visit four because you can
get information about one uh two and
three rather than immediately try to go
to two and three and that is uh yeah the
Hallmark of an active inference
agent yeah lot to explore here but
instead of relying on the post talk
comparison of energy terms this is in
reference to the way that usually
expected free energy is used by taking
in habit the policy prior and then
iterating over every element in pi the
policy prior and sharpening or updating
them according to the expected free
energy with the pragmatic value and the
epistemic value component so you get
some policy posterior and then you might
select simply the best one or you might
take some temperature guided sampling
across the policy posterior so that's a
post Haw comparison of expected free
energy terms and with
the that the gener models now have the
ability to directly infer
policy potentially
without explicit consideration of
counterfactuals or at the very least
without this kind of a post Hawk
comparison and so they build on that uh
and
create yeah a full
model and note
that in equation 47 they use a mix
mixture model of candidate transition
matrixes indexed by uh UK so each action
has a different transition
Matrix and yeah a buch of
illustrations and figure 28 shows an
agent that initially prefers the
epistemic action and so moves uh down to
State four and subsequently exhibits a
preference for either of the potentially
rewarding arms so goes left or right and
this shows that the loan active
inference is able to infer the optimal
policy and another approach can
reproduce P results of the
teamat and then the authors uh do it
again but now by adding a data
constraint and this is Sim similar to
using a maximum posterior
estimate which basically means that the
action is yes or no so it's 100% or
not Yeah by by pushing through the point
Mass constraint kind of like that derck
Delta
constraint all that can be shared is the
first moments which is just the data
points values so here it's like you
might have a 70% chance of doing thing
one 20% 2% 1% but then the action
selected is decisive and so you have
this decisive passing of action and the
the decisive realization of location
even if also there's like a location
distribution that includes Support over
the entire maze or a policy distribution
that includes support Over All
policies and then to conclude in this
paper we have proposed a Noel approach
to active inference Based On LAN
optimization which we have named Lan
active inference we demonstrated Lan
active inference on a classic Benchmark
problem for the the literature I found
that it inherence epistemic drive that
is hmark a hmark feature presents three
main advantages over previous algorithms
first and Advantage is the computational
efficienc afforded by being able to pass
backwards messages instead of needing to
perform forward houts for every policy
like aearch so it skills linearly over
time a second Advantage is that it
allows for directly inferring posteriors
Over Control signals instead of relying
on model comparison uh like Daniel just
explained and thirdly it is in heavly
modular and consequently works for
freely definable constraint for an
effector Cas while PR workers focused
mostly on specific generative models and
they have also introduced a notation for
writing down constraints and P
substitutions on a forny graph and the
constraint factor for graphs are useful
not only for active inference but for
specifying free energy functionals in
general and authors hope that this can
become a standard tool similar to foror
grass when it is desable not just right
the model but also a family of
distributions in the future work the
plan to extend uh the work to more node
constructions to further open the scope
uh that can be attacked with active
inference awesome work B great job
preparing it yakob anything you want to
add on part
one no at the moment okay scaling
linearly in time is really
fascinating like if you planned 10 time
steps should the 11th step be a
10% bump in difficulty or should it be
another combinatoric explosion every
little kilometer deeper into the
future so second
paper Okay first just going in deeply to
the first sentences before accelerating
across so they begin the paper saying
free energy principle postulates that
the behavor of biological agents can be
modeled as minimizing a variational free
energy and this is commonly brought up
that we can model biological agents as
or through or with minimizing
variational free energy just like saying
we can model this regression by fitting
an L2 Norm we can model this biological
agent by fitting the elbow or the VF
active inference which is aif in this
paper is a Cory of the Fe that describes
how agents propose effective agents by
minimizing an expected free energy
objective that internalizes a generative
model GM of the agent's environment and
prior beliefs about desired outcomes so
vfe is the real time Behavior
minimization EF brings it into the
prospective setting by introducing
epistemic imperative and also talking
about observations that haven't happened
yet variational objectives for active
inference can be minimized by message
passing on a forny style Factor graph
representation so everything we know
about basy and graphical models
transposes into the FFG space the FFG is
not a kind of base graph it is a dual a
different kind of graph conveying the
same information in a restructured
format that we can then optimize or
Implement
differently several authors have
attempted to scale active inference
under message passing framework however
agents based on these approaches lack
crucial epistemic
characteristics so one question why was
that was it that previous authors only
modeled vfe but not EF or was there some
failure of the EF loading on epistemic
value I think the answer is the first
one in part one they identified this
Hiatus in the specification
space and they introduced the C
FFG and and then in part two which is
the current paper we use the cffg
notation as introduced in part one to
Define locally constrained variational
objectives and derive variational
message updates for GFE generalized free
energy base control using variational
calculus the resulting control
algorithms introduce epistemic behavior
in synthetic active inference
agents we reason purely from an
engineering point of view and do not
concern ourselves with biological
plausibility what a
sentence in this paper our contributions
are three-fold they use variational
calculus to derive message update
expressions for GF control they derive
specialized messages for discrete
variable
model and they implement the results in
a reactive programming framework
simulating a perception action cycle on
the
Tas with a full message passing account
and reactive implementation of GF
optimization it Bec was possible to
derive and reuse custom message updates
across models and get a step closer to
realizing scalable synthetic active
inference agents for industrial
applications so what is it about their
contributions that makes the industrial
and the
engineering work more transferable or
scalable then they summarize the coming
sections section two reviews variational
base
section three reviews active inference
perception learning and control in terms
of message passing on the
cffg section four focuses on the
constraint definitions around a submodel
of two facing nodes hash Alis and Bob
and derives stationary Solutions and
messages for GF based control section
five applies the results to a specific
discrete variable goal observation subm
model that is often used in aif practice
they then work towards implementation in
a simulated setting and describe a
perception Action Cycle in terms of time
dependent constraints section six the
team A's task is described in section s
and simulated in a reactive programming
framework in Section 8 section n has a
summary of related work and the
conclusions are in section 10 it's also
useful to put table one and table two up
here table one is an overview of
notational
conventions nice list of letters would
be awesome to connect to the active
inference ontology and then table two
has a bunch of
acronyms okay section two review of
variational message passing so this
section briefly reviews variational
message passing as a distributed
approach to minimizing variational free
energy so first they review variational
base 2.1 then 2 . 2 they review forny
style Factor
graphs 2.3 they move to the Beth lran
optimization using the Grange
multipliers we can convert the
optimization on
Q to a free form optimization problem of
lran where the lran multipliers enforce
local
constraints the fully local optimization
then becomes this
expression
again more to say they're using the
lonian
constraint
framework and the Beth flavor of free
energy which is already node local to
provide a very constrained which is to
say possibly more solvable and tractable
node local
computation and now they get to the
constrain fory style Factor
graphs as we heard in part one an FFG
alone does not unambiguously define a
constrained vfe
objective interesting question what is
needed for that unambiguous
identification of the vfe and so here
they review their cffg notation here's
figure one and we can again see
that they go from the
initial Factor graph on the top
left with an explicit cffg on the top
right then they compress it down to the
bottom
left and
then that uniquely
identifies a logistical or an
operational
schedule section three review of active
inference by variational message passing
in this section we work towards a
message passing formulation of synthetic
active inference we start by reviewing
active inference and the cffg
representation for a GFE objective for
control so 3.1 they Define active
inference 3.2 they Define generative
model now they go to message
passing in this section we formulate a
synthetic active
inference uh as a message passing
procedure on a model of past and future
States in inference on a model of past
States relates to perception and
learning while inference on a model of
future States relates to
control what is control if not just
perception and learning we haven't had
yet figure three constraint 40 style
Factor graph representations for
variational objectives on models for
past left and future States
right I don't know if one has to cross
their eyes or do some other magic visual
experience here there are some small
differences like here there's a dashed
box that's not here there's a data
constraint clamp dangling edge here
whereas that constraint is open
here however the rest of the
figure looks pretty
similar and that tantalizingly point
points to some similarities
between learning and memory in the
past where we can clamp down part of the
model to be
data and consideration of the future
which is to say action and control where
the observations are distributional
beyond the dirck and they haven't
happened yet and we have agency over
them
happening any thoughts on that either of
you it's kind of cool and it's kind of
foraged in in some of the other
graphical models but we'll ask the
authors 331 talks about past States and
then 332 goes into the model of future
States so a lot to read in the paper but
that key idea because future outcomes
are by definition UNS observed we
include goal priors on the future
observation variables those are
preferences we expect there to be
observations and we know that they will
become constraint to derck likee form
but in anticipation we take a
distributional approach to observations
that haven't happened now what if we had
uncertainties out the past and we were
doing kind of
a policy like search in our fuzzy
memory then where would time
be section four they get to General GFE
based message
updates in the model for future States
the goal prior and observation model
impose simultaneous constraints on the
observation variable in the
corresponding cffg this configuration is
modeled by two facing
nodes so I
I believe those nodes might be the two
in the dashbox
here in this section we derive the
general GF based message updates for
paap facing notes we express the local
optimization problem as LR using
variational calculus we then derive St
local stationary solutions from which we
obtain General update expressions for GF
based
messages so they describe the the goal
and the obser ation
model 4.2 local
agian after the substitution of the
factorization and applying P
substitution to the local variational
free energy objective they get the local
GFE the GFE is all set up to construct
this
lran and to do a variational
optimization on that lran to get
qar
4.3 local stationary Solutions we are
now prepared to derive the stationary
points of the node local lran we start
by considering the node local lran as a
functional of the variational factor Q
subx LMA
one stationary points of L as a
functional of
Q what does LMA one do or
show LMA
two we derive stationary points of
equation four as a function of Q
subz note that by symmetry a similar
result applies to Q sub Theta what does
LMA 2 do or
show in this section we show that the
stationary Solutions of section 4.3
correspond to the fixed points of a
fixed Point iteration scheme theorem one
theorem two what of these theorems do
and show
4.5 conversions
considerations some further
considerations and a corollary One what
does it do or
show now we get to five application to a
discrete variable model in this section
we apply the general message update
rules of section 44 to a specific
discrete variable model that is often
used in aif practice using the general
results we derive messages on this
specific specific model and so here we
see figure
five
with all it's been taken all the way to
the point of the logistics of the
messages for those two facing
noes 53 data constrained message Updates
this uh the message updates for a data
constrained VF objective figure six on
the left reduced to standard variational
message passing updates as derived by
citation 28 and appendix a so here we
have those two nodes with the
dero
intervening here we had X intervening in
figure five so we had a
distributional
bandwidth now we're dealing with a d
distributional bandwidth or Channel
which is to say a data point being
passed now we to section six perception
Action Cycle in this section we
formulate a perception Action Cycle that
extends upon the GFE
formulation specifically we illustrate
how cffg notation allows us to be
explicit about local constraints as a
result the perception Action Cycle can
now be visualized as a process that
modifies constraints over time pretty
cool at the initial time T equals 1 no
observations are available and we
initialize the perception action cycle
with the cffg of figure 7 on the top we
got A Sneak Peak earlier now is real
figure
7 as actions are executed and
observations become available data
constraints replace the P substitution
on the observation variables so it's
almost like the P
substitution prepared us to flip it out
with data in some way like data
constraints are a a secondary or a
further
constraint that is enabled through the P
substitution when the time Horizon's
reached and all observations are
available on the
bottom data constraints replace the P
substitution on the observation
variables so it's kind of like we'll
know when we'll know and then it'll all
be inferenced like memory but before we
know what we later found out it's more
like
control so whether we're in a
retrospective memory setting a real time
sens making setting or a prospective
control theoretic setting it would be
pretty cool to have like a mega unified
imperative and ATT tractable local
procedure to do it which in a sense is
what they do so the perception action
cycle with time dependent constraints
thus unifies the tasks of perception
control and learning under a single
generative mod model and schedule this
is the huge piece is only through the
FFG and then the constrained
FFG can we get to not just making a base
graph of perception cognition and action
cool
enough bring in an explicit node local
scheduling and Logistics
approach wow the experimental protocol
is summarized in algorithm
one all it requires is a generative
model and a variational distribution
with Associated
constraints and then it's kind of like a
dance do infer act execute observe
slide we then get to section seven with
the experimental setting in this section
we describe a teas task that serves as a
classical setting for investigating
epistemic Behavior Citation 10 the setup
closely follows the definition in 30
Citation 10 is frisen at all 2015 active
inference and epistemic value and
citation 30 is from F Velar at all same
authors in 2022 active inference and
epistemic value and graphical models so
here we have the Tas that was shown
earlier with a smiley face no smiley
face here and it's laid out and labeled
starting position o q q c that's where
the epistemic value is and then L and R
the two reward arms and just for for
those seeking
continuity here's figure
7.4 from the 2022 textbook here we have
the 2022 active inference mouse in a
Tas and from 2021 here's our active
infer ants
simulation where it's actually
appropriate the nestmate is like much
smaller so for the nestmate they can
wander around a lot inside the
teas that for the mouse it only has one
location it can be in so it's not as
closely Allied as 7.4 is with figure
eight here but it's like the same you
could do it in the same
lap they further specify the the
teamas and the probabilities of
different things
happening they further specify the
teamas and the probabilities of things
happening and then in figure nine they
get to a
cffg describing the
teammates let's go through it with the
authors and annotate what it
means we have execute the same
experimental protocol as before and plot
the minimal free energies in figure 10
top
right the BFE based reference agent
fails to identify epistemic modes of
behavior the specific choice of Prior
for the observation Matrix prevents any
extrinsic information at least initially
from influencing policy
selection by the lack of an epistemic
Drive the BFE based agent sticks to
policies that confirm its prior belief
without exploring Poss possibilities to
exploit available information in the
tma's
environment a histogram of Ideal a
histogram of the number of wins per run
is plotted in figure 11 on the
left the histogram suggests a bodal
distribution with a large mass group to
the right and a smaller mass in the
middle for reference dashed curves
indicate ideal performance for agents
that already know a from the start for
agents that first must learn a
deviations from ideal performance are
expected the smaller middle mass then
indicates that GF optimization offers no
Silver Bullet for simulating fully
successful epistemic agents namely for
some choices of initialization the GF
agent may still become stuck in local
Optima section nine I won't read it they
describe a wide swath of related work
range in from early work on the
introduction of for graphs on through
expected free energy and active
inference and in section 10 they
conclude they took a constraint Centric
approach to synthetic Act of inference
they simulated a perception Action Cycle
through message passing derived from a
single generalized free energy objective
and dot dot dot in this paper we have
adopted a purely engineering point of
view and we have not concerned ourselves
with biological
plausibility specifically the derived
message updates come with considerations
about stability and non-standard
expressions although we have engineered
solutions to overcome these
complications it seems unlikely to us
that the brain resorts to such
strategies interesting mic
drop but very
humble and so now as we give our last
thoughts we've always held up the side
by side at The Institute with a minimum
of two and we've talked about that
before in the textbook figure 4.3
setting with continuous and discreete
time but there have been many other Min
too experiences that we've all shared
together and not just with this diad of
papers but with this new int
eligibility of the relationship between
Bas graphs and different styles and
constrained forms of for graphs we're in
yet another Min two setting
so say ining as we include the
zero
uh yeah I look forward to the point one
and point two have a bunch of questions
about for example what P substitution
really means and
um for example the the time window how
many uh time steps you need to give your
model
already or whether it can afford
automatically uh and just in general to
hear what they have to say because it is
a very interesting
topic
yeah um same here also interested to um
hear what the authors have to have to
say and um I
think yeah whenever there's um
um whenever there's a generalization
that um at least in the semantic space
uh
affords a wider
um wider connection to different methods
and especially in the context of uh
models represented on the graph I'd be
interested
to um learn more about how we can
represent agents in different kinds of
graphs or how these constraint for Stell
Factor graphs um afford different types
of uh optimization methods to be
performed on them
um and how this work can help active
inference to interface with uh other
domains which try to solve similar
problems or perhaps different problems
from a different
angle awesome my last thought is like we
planned to learn
learn at least to try here so I commend
you both for that policy selection and
now looking back it's like data or a
memory and then in science it's like oh
it's
1994 this new genome is available or
like this new thing is exciting and
here's the next step and it's
like one must be as excited as can be in
making the right measured decision then
which later becomes an
observation at a different time Point
yeah and a different
perspective
so there are probably
many exciting and important
syntheses that this work is going to
build our skills and our expressivity
around and the computational element is
just excellent
so thank you again Burt and yakup see
you Fells in the do
one all
right and